Register to The Henry Gilbert Papers
Yale University Music Library
- Writings, 1821-1928; Series IX; 6.7' (16 boxes)
  - Writings by Others, IX.B
    - Published or printed items belonging to Gilbert
      - New Latin reader. - New York: D. Appleton and company, 1882., Harkness, Albert
      - Harper's school geography. - New York: Harper & brothers, 1883.
      - North American Indian. - S.l.: s.n., no date, Hawthorne, Julian (Box 66, Folder 129)
      - Young folk's history of the United States. - Boston: Lee and Shepherd, 1875., Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911
      - Second reader for primary schools. - Boston: Brewer and Tileston, 1864., Hillard, G.S.
      - Hillard's fourth reader. - Boston: Brewer & Tileston, no date
      - Contemporary American composers. - Boston: L.C. Page, 1900., Hughes, Rupert, 1872-1956 (Box 67)
      - Essays before a sonata. - New York: Knickerbocker Press, 1920., Ives, Charles, 1874-1954
        Draft of autograph letter signed from Henry Gilbert to Ives (1920 May 26) was laid in.
      - How to win the war and the peace., [Kanazireff, V.] (Box 67, Folder 130)
        Unpublished copy of essay.
        Inscribed to Mrs. Henry Gilbert by the author, 1943 Aug.
      - Cape Cod Ballads. - Trenton: Albert Brandt, 1902., Lincoln, Joseph Crosby, 1870-1944
      - Elements of astronomy. - New York: D. Appleton and Company, 1876., Lockyer, J. Nor
      - Poems. - Boston: Ticknor and Fields, 1857., Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882
      - In memoriam., Makechnie, H.P. (Box 67, Folder 131)
        Printed on 1 sheet (3 copies), dated 1915 Jan.
      - Poems. - West Somerville, Mass.: s.n., 1902., Makechnie, H.P.
        Two copies, 1 with note laid in.
      - Art of music. - New York: National Society of Music, 1914., Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1873-1953
        Introductory no.
        See also: A. By Gilbert. Musical examples.
      - Slopes of Helicon. - Boston Estes and Lauriat, 1898., Mifflin, Lloyd
      - Mitchell's new general atlas. - Philadelphia: S. Augustus Mitchell, 1874.
      - Modern atlas. - Boston: Richardson & Lord, no date (Box 67, Folder 132)
      - Second reader. - Philadelphia: Cowperthwaite, c1873., Monroe, Lewis B.
      - History of religions. - New York: Charles Scribner's Songs, 1925., Moore, George Foot (Box 68)
      - Parsifal. - Boston: Richard G. Badger, 1904., Phelps, George Turner
        Inscribed by Author, 1904 Nov 14.
      - Pretty Poll: or a parrot's own history. - London; Edinburgh: T. Nelson & Sons, no date (Box 68, Folder 133)
      - Poems for pale people. - St. Louis: Humanity Printing and Publishing Company, c1906., Ranck, Edwin C. (Box 68, Folder 134)
        Inscribed by author, 1913 Dec 16.
        "Prosy examples and werse -- from the Peterboring Colony" - by Ranck (?) laid in (typescript. [15] leaves; 11 cm.).
      - History of music: vol. 1. - S.l.: s.n., 1909., Raymond, E.
      - Birthday offering. - New York: G. Schirmer, 1943., Reese, Gustave (ed.)
        No. 68 of 300 copies.
        Includes article by Downes re Henry Gilbert.
      - Principes d'orchestration. - Paris: Max Eschig, 1914., Rimsky-Korsakov, Nikolay, 1844-1908
      - Sonnets to myself. - S.l.: s.n., no date, Robinson, Donald Jay (Box 68, Folder 135)
      - Captain Craig. - New York: Macmillan Company, 1915., Robinson, Edwin Arlington (Box 69)
      - Collected poems. - New York: Macmillan Company, 1922., Robinson, Edwin Arlington
        Inscribed by author, 1923.
      - Dionysus in doubt. - New York: Macmillan Company, 1925., Robinson, Edwin Arlington
        Inscribed by author, 1925.
      - Tristam. - New York: Macmillan Company, 1927., Robinson, Edwin Arlington
        Inscribed by author, 1927 May 27.
      - Indian love letters. - Chicago: A.C. McClurg & Company, 1911., Ryan, Marah Ellis
        Inscribed by author, 1911 Nov 18.
      - Franklin written arithmetic. - Boston: William Ware, 1878., Seaver, E.P.
      - Love poems. - London; New York: John Lane, 1891., Shelley, Percy Bysshe, 1792-1822
      - Cyclopedia of Boston and vicinity. - Boston: Cashin & Smith, c1887., Smith, Dexter
      - Völsunga saga. - London: Walter Scott, 1888., Sparling, H. Halliday
      - Ballads of a lost house. - S.l.: s.n., no date, Speyer, Leonora, 1872-1956 (Box 69, Folder 136)
        Inscribed by the author, MacDowell Colony: 1924.
      - Stories from the Táin. - London: Williams & Norgate, 1928., Strachan, John
        Published for the Royal Irish Academy, Dublin: Hodges, Figgis & Company.
      - New language lessons. - New York: Harper & brothers, 1881., Swinton, William
      - Enoch Arden. - Boston: Ticknor and Fields, 1865., Tennyson, Alfred (Box 70)
      - Poetical works. - New York: Thomas Y. Crowell, no date, Tennyson, Alfred
      - Elements of psychology. - New York: A.G. Seiler, 1905., Thorndike, Edward L.
      - Illustrative practical arithmetic. - Boston: William Ware, 1877., Walton, George A.
      - Tetrology of Fallot. - Chicago: [American Medical Association], c1929., White, Paul D. (Box 70, Folder 137)
        Reprinted from The Journal of the American Medical Association, March 9, 1929, vol. 92, pp. 787-91.
        Re Henry Gilbert.
        See also: X. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL.
      - Soul of man under socialism. - Portland, Maine: Thomas B. Mosher, 1945., Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900
      - Modern atlas. - Hartford: Belknap and Hamersley, 1843., Woodbridge, William C. (Box 70, Folder 138)
        Notes and penmanship book belonging to Henry Gilbert's mother laid in.
      - Modern school geography. - Hartford: Belknap & Hamersley, no date, Woodbridge, William C.
      - Pronouncing spelling-book. - Boston: William Ware, c1873., Worcester, J.E.
- Biographical Material, 1928-1968; Series X; .4' (1 box)
  - [Read by Clarence C. Birchard at the funeral of Henry F. Gilbert], [Birchard, Clarence C.]; 3 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 71, Folder 1)
    Dated: ca. 1928 May.
  - Comment and criticism on the work of Henry F. Gilbert S.l.: s.n., no date (Box 71, Folder 2)
    Two copies each of two different brochures.
  - Family, 25 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 71, Folder 3)
    Re the Gilson family (Henry Gilbert's mother's side).
  - Biographical Material, 1928-1968; Furness, Clifton Joseph, 1898-1946; 3 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 71, Folder 4)
    Typescript with corrections by Mrs. Gilbert, and copy.
  - Genealogical record of Bailey, [6] p.; 18 cm. (Box 71, Folder 5)
  - Henry F. Gilbert S.l.: s.n., no date (Box 71, Folder 6)
    Proof sheet for?
  - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work, [10] sheets; 28 cm.
    - Henry F. Gilbert: the man and his work, 9 sheets; 28 cm.
  - Henry Y. Gilson family, [4] sheets; 33 cm. (Box 71, Folder 7)
    Typescript (photocopy).
  - Henry Franklin Belknap Gilbert, Howard, John Tasker; pp. 354-356; 28 cm. (Box 71, Folder 7)
    Copy of article in Our American music. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell, no date
  - Listing of Henry F. Gilbert's compositions, 21 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 71, Folder 8)
    Typescript and 4 copies.
  - Henry F. Gilbert: his life and works, Longyear, Katherine Marie Eide; xii, 281 p.; 28 cm. (Box 71, Folder 9-11)
    Copy of thesis "to fulfill the dissertation requirement for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy... Department of Music Theory... Eastman School of Music of the University of Rochester January, 1968."
    "List of examples from copyrighted material to be used in dissertation on the life and work of Henry F. Gilbert" (typescript, 2 sheets, 1967 Mar) - laid in.
  - Gilbert, Henry Franklin Belknap, Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995; p. 561; 30 cm. (Box 71, Folder 12)
    Article in Baker's... (5th edition).
    Proof sheet (negative), 3 sample copies (1 with note by Mrs. Gilbert), and 2 photocopies.
  - Tetrology of Fallot: report of a case in a noted musician, who lived to his sixtieth year. - Chicago: American Medical Association, c1929., White, Paul D. (Box 71, Folder 13)
    Two copies with markings.
    "Reprinted from the Journal of the American Medical Association March 9, 1929, vol. 92, pp. 787-91" - cover.
    See also: IX.B. WRITINGS. By Others.
  - Miscellaneous notes re Henry Gilbert by Henry Gilbert, [6] sheets; 28 cm. (Box 71, Folder 14)
    Typescripts with holograph annotations.
  - Untitled articles (Box 71, Folder 15)
    - Untitled articles, 2 sheets; 28 cm.
    - Untitled articles, 4 sheets; 28 cm.
  - Jottings re Henry Gilbert and his papers, Loose sheets ([26] p.). (Box 71, Folder 16)
- Photographs, 1850-1925; Series XI; 1.7' (4 boxes)
  This series is divided into two sections:
  Photograph albums
  Loose photographs - arranged alphabetically, oversize items are in box 73
  - Photograph albums
    Five photograph albums, 4 of which have had their covers removed for conservation purposes.
    - [Gilson family?], no date; [14] leaves; 14 x 22 cm. (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - [Gilson family, etc.], 1850-1903; [31] leaves; 14 x 21 cm. (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - [Gilbert, family, and friends], 1904-1925; [24] p.; 28 cm. (Box 72, Folder 3)
      Contains inscribed photographs of Edgar Stillman Kelley and [Arthur?] Shepherd. Also contains photographs of MacDowell Colony friends and others: Bartik, Breil, Chanler, Copland, Daniels, Hill, Humiston?, Kelley, Marian MacDowell, Narodny, Ranck, and Robinson.
    - [Scenery], no date; [22] leaves; 14 x 18 cm. (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - [Gilbert's family, etc.], no date; [28] p., bound; 16 cm. (Box 72, Folder 4)
  - Loose photographs
    - Glass plates, 16 items. (Box 73, Folder 5-9)
      Henry Gilbert and others.
    - Henry Gilbert, 43 items. (Box 73, Folder 10-18)
    - Others, ca. 248 items. (Box 73; 74; 75, Folder 19-23; 24-37; 38-41)
      Oversize items are in box 73, the rest are arranged alphabetically with the unidentified items at the end.
      Also includes photographic negatives and tintypes.
      Includes inscribed photos of Coon, MacDowell, and [Spear], as well as photos of Bartik and Denton.
      Includes a photogravure and a print of a photograph by Edward S. Curtis: "On the Nootka sound" inscribed, 1912; and "On the Spokane River," 1910, photogravure by John Andrew & Son.
- Engraver's Plates, no date; Series XII; 2.5' (12 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title within divisions by type of plate.
  - Photographic glass plates (negatives) of Henry Gilbert's music, 11 items. (Box 76, Folder 1-4)
    Includes plates for: Dollykins, Funny fact, Moon voyage, and Puzzled.
    Some plates are chipped, 1 plate is cracked.
  - Flat-bed offset lithographic plates of Henry Gilbert's music, 22 items. (Box 77; 78, Folder 5-8; 9-12)
    Untitled music.
    Includes 1 piece of slate.
  - Letterpress plates of text for notes re Henry Gilbert and his music, 20 items. (Box 79; 80; 81; 82; 83, Folder 13-16; 17-20; 21-24; 25-29; 30-32)
    Filed alphabetically by title.
  - Rotary offset lithographic plates of Henry Gilbert's music with engraved title pages., 37 items. (Box 84; 85; 86; 87, Folder 33-36; 37-39; 40-43; 44-47)
    Includes: Curl, Fishwharf rhapsody, Island of the Fay, Legend, Negro rhapsody, O were my love yon lilac fair, Owl, Perdita, and Scherzo.
- Sound Recordings, Series XIII
  Sound recordings have been transferred to the Historical Sound Recordings Collection in the Music Library. For further information about archival recordings relating to Henry Gilbert, please contact the Curator of Historical Sound Recordings.
- Miscellaneous Items, no date; Series XIV; 4' (5 boxes)
  This series is divided into eight sections:
  Music publisher's catalogues and brochures - Arranged alphabetically
  Scenic designs
  School merit cards and report card for Henry Gilbert - Arranged chronologically
  Business cards of Henry Gilbert and others - Arranged alphabetically
  Prints and sketches by Henry Gilbert and others
  Childhood sketchbooks, autograph albums, and notebooks of Henry Gilbert and others
  Miscellaneous items
  Realia - Three of these items remain unboxed (violin case and bows, 2 portraits)
  - Music publisher's catalogues and brochures, 64 items. (Box 88, Folder 1-8)
    Includes catalogues for the Wa-Wan Press.
  - Scenic designs
    - Dance in Place Congo (Box 88; 91, Folder 9; 10)
      Watercolor sketch (oversize), photograph of sketch, and 2 prints with ideas for scenic designs.
    - Fantasy in Delft (Box 88, Folder 11)
      Copy of a pencil or ink sketch of scenic design?
  - School merit cards and report card for Henry Gilbert, 13 items. (Box 88, Folder 12)
  - Business cards of Henry Gilbert and others, 14 items. (Box 88, Folder 13)
    Some contain notes.
  - Prints and sketches by Henry Gilbert and others, 41 items. (Box 88; 91, Folder 14-16; 17)
    Includes 2 oversize items.
  - Childhood sketchbooks, autograph albums, and notebooks of Henry Gilbert and others, 8 items. (Box 89, Folder 18-21)
  - Miscellaneous items, ca. 100 items. (Box 89; 91; 89; 90, Folder 22-23; 24-25; 26-29; 30-32)
    Includes invitations, advertisements, horoscope and phrenological readings of Henry Gilbert, tickets, bookplates, etc.
    Includes 5 oversize items.
  - Realia
    - Baby hair and bonnet, a Pilgrim half dollar (commemorating the Pilgrim Tercentenary celebration, 1920), 2 fans, etc., 7 items. (Box 90, Folder 33-35)
      There were originally 2 coins, 1 was kept and the other was transferred to the Yale Numismatic Collection.
    - Ruler (Box 91)
    - Rattle made of coconut and wood (Box 90)
      Made by Henry Gilbert "for use in playing the Comedy Overture(?)."
    - Pieces of two broken violins (Box 91)
      One probably made for Henry Gilbert by his father, note laid in.
    - Broken violin case and two bows
      Unboxed.
    - Death mask of Henry Gilbert (Box 93)
    - Two portraits of Henry Gilbert in oil
      By Robert W. Chanler.
      By Frank Waldo Murray.